Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- MISCELLANY, 344 numbered leaves, comprising 117 miscellaneous
  - Capitoli Concordati...Senato di Bologna li 14 Novembre 1708. Agreements between the city of Bologna and the Count of Tarn (?) concerning foreign and papal troops passing through the city and concerning hostages, dated Nov. 14, 1708, during the War of the Spanish Succession. 1 page (f. 77). (Box 106, Folder 13)
  - Copia de Capitoli del Agiustamento tra la Corte di Roma e di Vienna. Copy of an agreement, consisting of 14 points, between the courts of Rome and Vienna, dated Jan. 1709. 2 pages (f. 78). (Box 106, Folder 14)
  - Ristretto delle Capitolazioni concordate...delli 15 Gennario 1709, tra...Card. Paulucci...e...Marchese di Prié. Excerpts of the agreement in 22 points between Cardinal Paolucci for the Roman Church and the Marquis of Prié for the Emperor, dated Jan. 15, 1709. 4 pages, numbered ff. 79-80. (Box 106, Folder 15)
  - Points de Traité que le Roy de Suede a fait conclure entre le Roy Stanislas de Pologne et le Roy Electeur de Saxe publié le 14 Novembre 1706. 22 points of the Peace Treaty between Saxony and Poland. In French. 4 pages, numbered ff. 83-84. 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 16)
  - Oudenarden li 13 Luglio 1708. Draft of an account in Italian of the French defeat in Belgium by Prince Eugene of Savoy and Marlborough. Not signed, obviously by an eyewitness, enumerating casualties, prisoners taken, etc. 2 pages (f. 89). 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 17)
  - Li progretti di pace fatti proponere nuovamente. 14 Febraio 1710. Preliminary peace proposals to bring the War of the Spanish Succession to an end. 1-1/2 pages (f. 86). (Box 106, Folder 18)
  - Proposizioni ereticali abiurate del Sacerdote D. Giuseppe Beccarelli...nella Piazza del Duomo di Brescia. Giuseppe Beccarelli (1666-1716), priest in Urago d'Oglio, near Brescia, was accused of heretical views and condemned by Giovanni Badoer, Cardinal of Brescia, on 13 Sept., 1710, to prison for life. With a copy of a letter by the Venetian Senate to Cardinal Badoer. 2 leaves, numbered ff. 87 and 89. Large folio, folded. (Box 106, Folder 19)
  - Copia Pacis Inter Czarum et Sultanum. Copy of the Peace terms in Latin between Peter I and the Turks, dated July 12, 1711. 4 pages, numbered ff. 91-92. 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 20)
  - (Conclave of 1689). The original ballot, printed in red and black, of the Conclave of 1689 which elected Pietro Vito Ottoboni as Pope Alexander VIII on October 6. The names of the voting clerics are printed in black on red lines with some names (of other candidates?) added in ink. 1 page (f. 92). Double folio, folded. (Box 106, Folder 21)
  - Notizie del Conclave per la Morte di Papa Innocenzo XI...per l'eletione di Papa Alessandre VIII creato le 6 Ottobre 1689. Daily record of the conclave of 1689 that sat from Aug. 24 to Oct. 6, before the final vote was cast. With a list of the voting Cardinals, giving the dates of their birth and of their appointment. 4 pages, numbered ff. 93-94. (Box 106, Folder 22)
  - Notizie del Conclave per la morte di Papa Alessandro VIII...per l'elettione di Papa Innocenzio XII. Daily record of the Conclave of 1691 that sat from Feb. 21 to July 12, before the final vote was cast. 4 pages, numbered ff. 96-97. (Box 106, Folder 23)
  - Notizie del Conclave per la morta di Papa Innocenzo XII...per l'elettione di Papa Clemente XI... Daily record of the Conclave of 1700 that sat from Oct. 31 to Nov. 23, when the final vote was cast for Clement XI. With a list of the voting Cardinals, giving their dates of birth and of their appointment. 4 pages, numbered ff. 98-99. (Box 106, Folder 24)
  - (Comparative table of monetary values). Comparing the scudo with money of the Papal States, the giulio and the baiacco. 3 pages, numbered ff. 100-101. (Box 106, Folder 25)
  - Conto di Spese fatte nella Villeggiatura di Vicovaro... A detailed account of the moneys spent during a vacation in Vicovaro (near Tivoli) from October 7 to December 27, 1708; the accounts are specified as to food, beverages, carriages and horses, tips, etc. In 2 columns. 4 pages, numbered ff. 102-103. (Box 106, Folder 26)
  - Crispino, Giuseppe. Memoriale contra la monache d'Amelia. A memoir by Giuseppe Crispino (c. 1635- 1721), Bishop of Amelia, on the state of the monasteries of the diocese of Amelia. 4 pages, numbered ff. 104-105. In 1702, Crispino published Relatio Status Ecclesiae Amerinae ad Clementum XI. (Box 106, Folder 27)
  - Historici Successi di Monsignore Crispino Vescovo de Amelia. Biographical notices on outstanding bishops, probably in reference to Crispino's Il Boun Vescovo, 1685 and mentioning his Relatio Status Ecclesiae Amerinae (see above, no. 27). 8 pages, numbered ff. 106-109. 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 28)
  - Proviste Uscita Primo Gennaro 1708. Lists of clerical appointments on the first of January, 1708. 6-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 110-113. (Box 106, Folder 29)
  - Nota di Proviste fatta da N.S... List of clerical appointments, dated Aug. 21, 1708. 2 pages (f. 114). (Box 106, Folder 30)
  - Nota di Proviste fatta da N.S... List of clerical appointments of Aug. 16, 1709. 3 pages, numbered ff. 115-116. (Box 106, Folder 31)
  - Mutationi e Proviste fatta da N.S... List of clerical appointments, dated Dec. 8, 1709. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 116-117. (Box 106, Folder 32)
  - Governatori. List of governors in the various provinces of Italy, undated. 2 pages (f. 118). (Box 106, Folder 33)
  - 3 Ottobre, 1708. Statutes concerning a monastery. 1 page (f. 119). (Box 106, Folder 34)
  - Nuovo...per la Dame nell'Anno 1708. Directions for ladies going to church, in 8 points. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 120 and 122. (Box 106, Folder 35)
  - Carlo e Mauritio D'Aste, Monserrato. Short letter addressed to them, dated July 19, 1709. 1 page and address (f. 121). Oblong 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 36)
  - (A list of druggists, butchers, fruit vendors, etc.). with their addresses in Rome, dated 1708. 1 page (f. 123). 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 37)
  - La Reverenda Camera Apostolica alla Santita di...Papa Clemente XI. A long letter in Italian, undated and unsigned, to Pope Clement XI (1700-1721). 33 pages numbered ff. 124-140. (Box 106, Folder 38)
  - Protesta del Tribunale della Camera, alla...Papa Clemente XI, 1708. 9 pages, numbered ff. 142-146. (Box 106, Folder 39)
  - Oratio habita a...Clem. XI in Consistorio...16 Martii 1712 in Morte Delphini... Latin speech by Pope Clement XI on occasion of the death of Charles VI's nephew, who died Feb. 18, 1712. 2 pages (f. 148). (Box 106, Folder 40)
  - (Louis XIV). Discorso del Re Christianissimo al Re Giacomo III della Gran Bretagna...Scotia, Marzo 1708. Louis XIV's discourse to James III, in Italian. 3 pages, numbered ff. 149-150. (Box 106, Folder 41)
  - Orsini, Cardinal. Lettera al Papa (Clement XI). Copy in Italian, dated Jan. 17, 1708. 7 pages, numbered ff. 156-159. (Box 106, Folder 42)
  - Paolucci, Cardinal. Copia di lettera...al Card. Pignatelli...16 di Giugno 1708. Letters concerning the edicts of Naples and Milan. 4 pages, numbered ff. 160-161. (Box 106, Folder 43)
  - Dispaccio in Data de 18 Feb. 1708 da Barcellona... 3 Dispatches from Barcelona of Feb. and March 1708 concerning the edicts of Milan and Naples. 4 pages, numbered ff. 163-164. (Box 106, Folder 44)
  - Dispaccio...da Barcellona... 2 dispatches, dated Barcelona and Naples, March 1708, concerning the edicts of Milan and Naples. 1-1/2 pages (f. 165). (Box 106, Folder 45)
  - Joseph I. Lettera a Papa Clemente XI... Copy of a letter in Italian, written by the Emperor to Clement XI on July 9, 1708, concerning Naples and Milan. 3 pages, numbered ff. 166-167. (Box 106, Folder 46)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo. Lettera a vescovi di Regno...28 Luglio 1708...contre le Persone destinate ad esigere Le Rendite de Beneficii ecclesiastici. Copy of a letter by Cardinal Grimani, then Viceroy of Naples. 2 pages (f. 168). (Box 106, Folder 47)
  - (Bartholomaeus Gambadoro, Bishop of Ruvo). Letter in Italian to Cardinal Grimani, Viceroy of Naples, dated Aug. 11, 1708. 1 page (f. 169). (Box 106, Folder 48)
  - Archinto, Cardinal Giuseppe. Copy of a letter to Cardinal Paolucci, dated July 4, 1708. - Charles III. Copy of a letter to Cardinal Giuseppe Archinto, dated July 20, 1708. 2 pages (f. 171). (Box 106, Folder 49)
  - Lettera Circolante scritta del Segretaria di Stato à Tutti i Vescovi del Regno di Napoli, e Stato di Milano...concernente gli Sequestri de Beneficii eccli. Copy of a circulatory letter by Cardinal Paolucci to the Bishops of Milan and Naples, July 6, 1708. 2 pages (f. 172). (Box 106, Folder 50)
  - Clement XI, Pope. Copy of a letter in Latin to Cardinal Vincenzo Grimani, dated Sept. 1, 1708, when he was Viceroy of Naples. 5 pages, numbered ff. 174-176. (Box 106, Folder 51)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo, Viceroy of Naples. Copy of a letter in Italian, dated Naples, Sept. 22, 1708, and referring to the circulatory letter (see above, no. 50). 2 pages (f. 178). (Box 106, Folder 52)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo, Viceroy of Naples. of a letter in Italian, dated Naples, Sept. 20, 1708, Marquis of Prié (?). 6 pages, numbered ff. 179-181. (Box 106, Folder 53)
  - Carpegna, Gaspare, Cardinal. Copy of a letter in Italian to Cardinal Vincenzo Grimani, Viceroy of Naples, dated Rome, Oct. 13, 1708. With Grimani's answer to him, dated Naples, Oct. 20, 1708. 4 pages, numbered ff. 183-184. (Box 106, Folder 54)
  - Riflessi sopra Liti mori per l'edito di Carlo in Napoli e Milano 1708. Document in Italian. Unsigned. 8 pages, numbered ff. 187-190. (Box 106, Folder 55)
  - Copia di Biglietto da un Cavaliere d'onore della Regina Vedova di Bolonia al Cardinal Gualtieri. La Sera Praecedente al...de Consistorio Publico... Copy of a letter to Cardinal Gualtieri, dated March 22, 1708. 1 page (f. 191). (Box 106, Folder 56)
  - Moles, Duca. Copy of a letter in Italian to Cardinal Orsini in Barcelona, of April 28, 1708. 4 pages, numbered ff. 192-193. (Box 106, Folder 57)
  - Prié, Marquis de, and Pope Clement XI. Correspondence in Italian, concerning a proposal made by Prié, in copies. One letter dated Sept. 20, 1708. 23 pages, numbered ff. 197-208. (Box 106, Folder 58)
  - Tessé, J.B.R. de Froulay. Copy of a letter in Italian to Pope Clement XI, Dated Dec. 16, 1708. Tessé was at the time the Plenipotentiary of Louis XIV in Rome. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 209-210. (Box 106, Folder 59)
  - Tessé, J.B.R. de Froulay. Copies of 2 more letters in Italian to Pope Clement XI, dated Jan. 2, 1709 and Feb. 13, 1709. 3 pages, numbered ff. 211-212. (Box 106, Folder 60)
  - Monte Albano, Duke Osseda, Count di. Copy of a letter by the ambassador of Philip V of Spain to the Pope, probably Clement XI. Undated. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 214-215. (Box 106, Folder 61)
  - Bonneval, Alexander von. Copy of an edict published by the general of the Imperial troops in Comacchio, July 8, 1708. The Imperial troops under Bonneval had taken Comacchio on May 24, 1708. 2 pages (f. 216). (Box 106, Folder 62)
  - Grimani, Cardinal Vincenzo. Copy of a letter to Paolucci, dated June 29, 1708. 4 pages, numbered ff. 217-218. (Box 106, Folder 63)
  - (Paolucci, Cardinal Fabrizio). Copy of Paolucci's answer to Grimani's letter of June 29, concerning Comacchio. Dated July 6, 1708. 6-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 220-223. (Box 106, Folder 64)
  - Joseph I. Copy of a letter, written by the Emperor to all Cardinals, concerning the status of Parma and Piacenza, dated June 27, 1708. 2 pages (f. 224). (Box 106, Folder 65)
  - (Clement XI, Pope). Declaratio Nullitatis...super hybernis stationibus quas Milites Germani in Ducatu Parmae, & Placentiae locarunt. Printed Papal breve against the German positions in Parma and Piacenza of July 27, 1707. 12 pages, withthe Papal arms on the title. Romae, ex typog. Rev. Cam. Apost., 1707. 4to, uncut. 12 pages, numbered in ink ff. 227-229. (Box 106, Folder 66)
  - Clement XI. Copy of a breve, dated June 2, 1708, addressed to Victor Amadeus II, Duke of Savoy, concerning the German invasion of Comacchio. With a copy of the answer by the Duke, dated June 27, 1708. 2 pages (f. 230). (Box 106, Folder 67)
  - Carpegna, Cardinal Gaspare. Copy of a letter to Cardinal Grimani, Viceroy of Naples, dated July 21, 1708, concerning Joseph I's letter to the Cardinals of June 27 (see above, no. 65). With Grimani's answer to Carpegna, dated Aug. 4, 1708. 7 pages, numbered ff. 231-234. (Box 106, Folder 68)
  - S. Collegio dei Cardinali. Copy of a letter in Latin to the Cardinal of Saxony, dated Aug. 12, 1708. 2 pages (f. 235). (Box 106, Folder 69)
  - (S. Collegio dei Cardinali?). Copy of a letter in Latin to Emperor Joseph I. Dated Rome, Aug. 12, 1708. 7 pages, numbered ff. 236-239. 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 70)
  - Lettera di N.S. all'Imperatore. Copy of a letter in Latin by Pope Clement XI to Emperor Joseph I, 1708. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 241-242. (Box 106, Folder 71)
  - (Philip V of Spain). Copy of a letter in Italian, written by Giovanni Milan di Aragon, dated Madrid, June 19, 1709, addressed to Rome, announcing the closing of the nunciature in Madrid and of any commerce with Rome. 3-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 243- 244. (Box 106, Folder 72)
  - Medici, Giovanni Gastone d', Grand Duke of Tuscany. Copy of a letter to Cardinal Lod. M. Pandolfini of Bologna, dated Florence, June 19, 1709. 1 page (f. 245). (Box 106, Folder 73)
  - Medici, Giovanni Gastone d', Grand Duke of Tuscany. Copy of a letter to Card. Lod. M. Pandolfini, July 23, 1709. 1 page (f. 246). (Box 106, Folder 74)
  - Saverio Azzoni, F. Francesco. Copy of a letter to Ulisse Vincenti in Rome, dated Malta, Oct. 25, 1709. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 247-248. 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 75)
  - Perellos. Copy of a letter to Sacchetti in Rome, dated Malta, Oct. 25, 1709. 2 pages (f. 249). 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 76)
  - Bouglione, Cardinal. Copy of a letter in Italian to King Louis XIV of France, dated May 22, 1710. 3 pages, numbered ff. 248-249. (Box 106, Folder 77)
  - Louis XIV, King of France. Copy of a letter, in Italian, by the King of France to his ambassador in Rome, Cardinal Trémoille, dated Paris, July 10, 1710. 3 pages, numbered ff. 250-251. (Box 106, Folder 78)
  - Assumar, Cardinal, Ambassador of Portugal in Barcelona. Copy of a letter in Italian to Signor Inviato of Portugal in Rome, dated Saragozza, Aug. 22, 1710. 3 pages, numbered ff. 252-253. (Box 106, Folder 79)
  - Gigli, Marcus. Copy of a letter in Latin to Gregorio d'Aste, dated Rome, Oct. 1710. 3 pages, numbered ff. 254-255. (Box 106, Folder 80)
  - (Rome, April 21, 1712). Account in Italian of a church procession in Rome celebrating the canonization of Pius V (May 5, 1712) by Pope Clement XI. 3 pages, numbered ff. 256-257. (Box 106, Folder 81)
  - Aelius, Sex. Acropolitanus. Ad Eumenem Parthenium Epistolae. Printed letter in Latin. 8 pages, numbered in ink ff. 258-261. N.p., 1700. Apparently a very rare theological letter, not in the BM or BN catalogues. (Box 106, Folder 82)
  - Cloche, Antonin. Salutem...& Mortis Recordationem. Printed oration in Latin on the death of Horatio Albani, brother of Pope Clement XI, by A. Cloche, General of the Dominicans. Dated Rome, Jan. 29, 1712. 2 pages (numbered in ink f. 262). Apparently very rare, not in the catalogues of the BM or BN. (Box 106, Folder 83)
  - Titoli et honori che concede S.M. Cesarea. List of the titles and honors granted by the Emperor, probably Joseph I, and the amount of money that went into the titles. Undated. 4 pages, numbered ff. 263-264. Folio, folded. (Box 106, Folder 84)
  - (Latin Sermon on Martyrs). Undated and unsigned. 3 pages, numbered ff. 265-266. (Box 106, Folder 85)
  - L'Officio del Segretario di Camera in Ferrara. A brief of complaint, undated and unsigned, concerning certain posts being taken over by secular officials. 3 pages, numbered ff. 267-268. (Box 106, Folder 86)
  - (Collegio Germanico--Ungarico, Roma). Examen pro admittendis inter alumnos Colegii Germanici, & Ungarici Urbis. A printed Latin questionnaire for admittance into the Jesuit Collegium Germanicum- Ungaricum, which was founded in Rome in 1552. The questionnaire, consisting of 29 questions altogether, contains the questions in the left column; the right column, headed Responsiones, is left free for the answers to be filled in. 4 pages, numbered in ink ff. 273-274. (Box 106, Folder 87)
  - (Innocent XI, Pope). Resolution to reduce the cost of canonizations. Report, in Italian, by several Cardinals, with specified lists of the costs. It seems that Innocent XI (1676-1689) had appointed a fact-finding committee to study the problem. The present report is approved on the last page, with the date July 20, 1690. 8 pages, numbered ff. 275-278. (Box 106, Folder 88)
  - Feria S. Die 8 Augusti 1709. Document in Latin, concerning the long feud between Rome and the Jesuit missionaries in China, who practiced unorthodox rites, referring to earlier decrees of 1704 and 1707, to Thournon, etc. 2 pages (f. 279). (Box 106, Folder 89)
  - (Maxamilien Emanuel, Elector of Bavaria). Protestatio Serenissimi Electoris Bavariae. Printed text, with Latin and Italian in facing columns. Dated Namur, July 7, 1711. 4 leaves (the last is blank), paginated a-f (numbered in ink ff. 280-283). N.p., n.d. (Box 106, Folder 90)
  - Mattei, Monsignor. Orazione fatta nel sua publico Ingresso della Nunziatura in Venezia li 5 Ottobre 1711. Copy of the speech, together with the copy of the answer. 4 pages, numbered ff. 285-286. Large folio, folded. (Box 106, Folder 91)
  - Carpegna, Cardinal Gaspare. A short note in Latin, dated Sept. 22, 1711, with a postscript of Sept. 23, concerning José Molines, General Inquisitor of Spain. 1 page (f. 287). Oblong 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 92)
  - Pasquino Viandanto, ò Papagiero. A long Italian satirical poem in tercets, on events in the Roman Church, missions, etc., dated 1708. The names of some of the persons alluded to in the poem are given in marginal notes. 27 pages, numbered ff. 288-301. (Box 106, Folder 93)
  - A Monsig. Monti. -Al Sig. Pier Luigi Loccarini (Lucarini). Two Italian satirical poems in tercets, concerning missionaries. 5 pages, numbered ff. 302-304. (Box 106, Folder 94)
  - Al Sig. Pomeo Bevardi. Italian poem in two parts: a satire in tercets with many of the persons alluded to named in marginal notes. Unsigned and undated. 10 pages, numbered ff. 306-311. (Box 106, Folder 95)
  - Al Sig. Monaldi. Italian poem in praise of Carlo Monaldi (c. 1690-1760), Roman sculptor. Undated, unsigned. 4 pages, numbered ff. 312-313. Large folio, folded. (Box 106, Folder 96)
  - Sermo Primus. Latin sermon in hexameters, with notes at the end, giving explanations in Italian and the names of the persons alluded to, among them the painter and cariacturist Pietro Ghezzi, a.o. Undated and unsigned. 6 pages, numbered ff. 314-316. (Box 106, Folder 97)
  - Sonnet. Draft of an Italian sonnet on love. 1 page (f. 318). (Box 106, Folder 98)
  - Fatt'hormai falegname, o Dio d'Amore. A sonnet, signed H.H. 1 page (f. 319). (Box 106, Folder 99)
  - Ceciliae Turchiae Romanae. A Latin poem, unsigned and undated. 1 page (f. 320). (Box 106, Folder 100)
  - Per la Morte dell'Imperatore. Italian sonnet on the death of the Emperor (Joseph I (?), d. 1711). 1 page (f. 321). (Box 106, Folder 101)
  - Particulas Vini, puras quas reddidit ignis. A short Latin poem, ending "ad Aram Pectinis Etruscum carmen in obsequium." 1 page (f. 322). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 102)
  - Sonnet. An Italian sonetto. 1 page (f. 323). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 103)
  - Porporato Signore a te'm'invia. Italian poem. 2 pages (f. 324). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 104)
  - Per Illustrissima Signora Maria d'Aste. Italian sonnet. 1 page (f. 325). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 105)
  - Nelle partenza da Roma da 3 (Juli 1708) del Marchese Morbelli. Italian sonnet. 1 page (f. 326). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 106)
  - L'Imperatrice Madre a Giuseppe Primo. -Risposta delle Imperatore all'Imperadrice Madre. Two sonnets: to Joseph from his mother and his answer to her. 2 pages, numbered ff. 327-328. 4to. (Box 106, Folder 107)
  - Di casto Amor la nobil face accessa. Italian sonnet. 1 page (f. 329). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 108)
  - Bellezze della Diva d'Apollo. Italian sonnet. 1 page (f. 330). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 109)
  - Firsi Sol del mio Cor. Italian sonnet. 1 page (f. 331). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 110)
  - ...Fido Amante. Italian love poem. 1 page (f. 332. 4to. (Box 106, Folder 111)
  - Sonetto. Italian sonnet, with corrections and a small sketch of a church. 1 page (f. 333). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 112)
  - Amore regniato con infida amante. Italian sonnet. 1 page, numbered ff. 334. 4to. (Box 106, Folder 113)
  - (Italian sonnet). 1 page (f. 335). 4to. (Box 106, Folder 114)
  - Squarcio all'Iberia col. rapace artiglio. -D'Anglia, d'Austria, d'Olanda il furor misto. 2 sonnets concerning the War of the Spanish Succession. 2 pages (f. 341). 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 115)
  - Risolvo e dio adesso in tutta fretta. Italian poem. 1 page (f. 342). 8vo. (Box 106, Folder 116)
  - Nel vedersi il Ritratto della Signora Propesta Ruffo di Bueno... -Propesta del C.N.N. -Risposta. Three sonnets. 3 pages, numbered ff. 343-344. 4to. (Box 106, Folder 117)